<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en_US"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://samgrayson.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://samgrayson.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en_US" /><updated>2019-08-02T03:10:43-05:00</updated><id>https://samgrayson.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Interesting Thoughts</title><subtitle>Blog about computers, mathematics, and philosophy. Occasionally, other people find my thoughts on these topics interesting.</subtitle><author><name>Samuel Grayson</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Chaos of History (part 2)</title><link href="https://samgrayson.me/2017-01-09-chaos-of-history-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Chaos of History (part 2)" /><published>2017-01-09T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2017-01-09T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://samgrayson.me/chaos-of-history-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samgrayson.me/2017-01-09-chaos-of-history-2/">&lt;p&gt;In a
&lt;a href=&quot;/2016-07-21-chaos-of-history-1/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;,
I talked about how a few random events can greatly change history. In this
post, I will describe that idea more mathematically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-gedanken&quot;&gt;A Gedanken&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say I throw a rock straight up into the air and measure how far away it
falls 10000 times. &lt;em&gt;I have too much free time.&lt;/em&gt; I can plot that distance against
the number of falls. You would expect most of them to fall very close to where I
threw the rock. You would expect far-away falls to be pretty rare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We might suggest that this fits a Gaussian distribution (that’s what most people
associate bell-curve). Most physical phenomena roughly follow a Gaussian
distribution. Towards the far right, the probability is very small. It should be
rare that I would toss a rock straight up in the air and see it land 20 meters
away. The far left and far right are called the ‘tails’ of the distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Gaussian distribution&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/chaos-of-history-2/gaussian_distribution.png&quot; style=&quot;margins: auto;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;haphazard-stroll&quot;&gt;Haphazard stroll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s say I throw the rock in the air, but this time I walk to where it
landed and throw the rock in the air again from that point. This is called a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Random_walk&quot;&gt;random walk&lt;/a&gt;, and here is what it
looks like when the rock falls based on a Gaussian distribution. For good
measure, I will run 5 random walks starting from different spots in different
colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Gaussian random walk&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/chaos-of-history-2/gaussian_random_walk.png&quot; style=&quot;margins: auto;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I want to talk about another distribution: the Cauchy distribution. It is
very similar to the Gaussian distribution, but it is ever-so-slightly higher at
the tails (hence it is called a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fat-tailed_distribution&quot;&gt;fat-tailed distribution&lt;/a&gt;).
This means that extreme outcomes are still rare, but slightly less rare. People
often too quick to assume that a bell-curve shaped distributions are Gaussian,
as
&lt;a href=&quot;http://rocketscienceofwallstreet.blogspot.com/2012/04/nassim-nicholas-taleb-against-gaussian.html&quot;&gt;some would argue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Gaussian and Cauchy distribution&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/chaos-of-history-2/gaussian_and_cauchy.png&quot; style=&quot;margins: auto;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the difference seems small. Let’s see how these distributions differ in a
real experiment. I’ll take a random walk using the Cauchy distribution and look
at the differences&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Cauchy random walk&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/chaos-of-history-2/cauchy_random_walk.png&quot; style=&quot;margins: auto;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Gaussian random walk, no single rock-throw really moved us far from the
origin. None of the throw were really ‘out there’. In each Cauchy random walk,
most of the throws didn’t affect the outcome that much, but there were one or two
really impactful throws that did most of the moving (especially in the blue and
green random walk). Outliers are still rare, but when they do occur, they are
&lt;strong&gt;hugely influential&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-historical-analogy&quot;&gt;The historical analogy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest that many historical phenomena act have analogous behavior. One example
might be, the assassination of Arch Duke Franz Ferdinand; another might be the
Gulf of Tonkin incident, 9/11, or the battle of Thermopylae.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; historical trends and forces, but they are often realized by single
explosive events. There was a general trend of anti-imperialism in the early
twentieth century. Even though most movements of that trend were minor, it only
took one explosive assassination to change world history irrevocably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-to-the-future&quot;&gt;Looking to the future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;average value&lt;/em&gt; of a Gaussian or Cauchy distribution is zero (move neither
to the left or to the right). &lt;em&gt;On average&lt;/em&gt;, when we throw the rock straight up,
it lands on top of me. The left moves will cancel out the right moves and it
will end up not far from where starts (the distribution is symmetric). The
&lt;em&gt;average&lt;/em&gt; may be easy to predict, but &lt;em&gt;reality&lt;/em&gt; might be different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Gaussian random walk, most of the moves are medium. In the Cauchy most of
the moves are very small, or very large. A few very extreme moves cause most of
the movement away from the expected value. As a result, the average predicts
reality quite poorly. It would have been completely debunked by any one of those
extreme moves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why markets are so difficult to predict. There are a few
unpredictable and extreme events which cause most of the movement
(called “black swan events”). On average, prices are constant or
increasing steadily (due to inflation), but then the OPEC declares an
embargo and the price of oil becomes 300% larger. Or hurricane Katrina
hits. That is an unlikely and extreme event that screws up the
models. &lt;a href=&quot;https://dollarvigilante.com/blog/2016/08/09/nassim-taleb-warns-biggest-black-swan-event-coming.html&quot;&gt;Some
argue&lt;/a&gt;
that lack of recognition of black swan events played a part in causing
the housing crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should we try harder to predict black swan events with models? There
will never be enough data-points to do useful analysis of them because
of their characteristic rarity. The best we can do is remember that
every model is fallible and engineer the robustness necessary to
handle that fallibility. These are “unknown unknowns” in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/There_are_known_knowns&quot;&gt;the parlance
of Donald Rumsfeld&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t confuse unlikely with impossible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Grayson</name></author><category term="math" /><category term="history" /><summary type="html">In a previous post, I talked about how a few random events can greatly change history. In this post, I will describe that in terms of mathematics and use that to show you why things like stock markets are so difficult to predict.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samgrayson.me/assets/img/chaos-of-history-2/jackson_pollock.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Zealots of Tech</title><link href="https://samgrayson.me/2016-08-12-zealots-of-tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zealots of Tech" /><published>2016-08-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-08-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://samgrayson.me/zealots-of-tech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samgrayson.me/2016-08-12-zealots-of-tech/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;welcome-to-the-cult&quot;&gt;Welcome to the Cult&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are few techniques that are globally applicable in software
development. But we like to act is if that were not the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is most apparent in programming languages. You have headstrong
engineers who insist that their programming language is better than
yours, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/haskell/comments/3of8zk/the_cult_of_haskell_is_my_favourite_programming/&quot;&gt;cult-like
devotion&lt;/a&gt;.
Most of the time, programming languages have different strengths and
weaknesses, so the ‘best’ programming language depends on the
problem. It is religious zealotry when they don’t hear out arguments
against their language of choice. But that insistence is mostly
unfounded. Look at the sentiment on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/What-are-the-best-programming-languages-to-learn-today&quot;&gt;this quora
question&lt;/a&gt;
on the ‘best programming language’ with many comments like “depends on
what you want to optimize” and “it’s far more important to learn to be
a good programmer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managers and investors have a different set of biases about
programming languages: they insist on using what everyone else is
using. They know that Java on tomcat is a popular choice for web
development. They block out other options like Ruby on Rails, which
might better suit a startup that needs to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.minddigital.com/ruby-on-rails-for-robust-and-rapid-development/&quot;&gt;go from 0 to
60&lt;/a&gt;,
because of their fundamentalist belief that some programming language
or technique is the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; way. What’s worse is when they prevent an
innovative solution from being developed because “it’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://paulgraham.com/icad.html&quot;&gt;not industry
standard&lt;/a&gt;.” &lt;em&gt;Aside: That utterance is
the sound of a good idea dying an unnecessary death in a company that
reeks of mediocrity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;critical-thinking&quot;&gt;Critical Thinking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some value in using languages you have deep prior knowledge
of, but there is also value in keeping your mind sharp by learning new
things. Technology is changing so fast that the tools you feel
comfortable with may not be relevant anymore. There is also value in
using a technique that has a large community for support, but that
argument is often weighed too heavily against other, more direct
advantages (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://waitbutwhy.com/2015/11/the-cook-and-the-chef-musks-secret-sauce.html&quot;&gt;Tim Urban’s
post&lt;/a&gt;
at headline “The Cook and the Chef”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human tendency is to jump on the hype bandwagon and follow the
crowd. It is the underlying habit of humans to fall into
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Groupthink&quot;&gt;groupthink&lt;/a&gt; caused by
laziness. It isn’t an overt laziness like shirking duty or skipping
work, it is a subconscious laziness that avoids critical evaluation of
one’s own opinions. It isn’t too dissimilar from the echo-chamber of
our political environment, or a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Emperor%27s_New_Clothes&quot;&gt;naked
emperor&lt;/a&gt;
who claims that only the intelligent are able to see his new clothes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next time you hear “do this because it is more RESTful”, you
should ask yourself “why are we embracing REST here. Does it make
sense?” That way you justify your design decisions based on the
problem itself, not some principle you have forced your solution to
conform to. Don’t be afraid to question the prevailing wisdom like a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_gadfly&quot;&gt;gadfly&lt;/a&gt;. “Yes, I know
this diverges from the principles of REST, but our multi-part search
query isn’t conducive to RESTful URI design since the components are
not hierarchical.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I leave you with the old Unix adage of pragmatism: &lt;em&gt;use the right tool
for the job&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Grayson</name></author><category term="programming" /><summary type="html">There are few technologies and methodologies that are globally applicable in software development, be it REST, agile methodology, or Python. But we like to act is if that were the case. Instead flexible and pragmatic enough to use the right tool for the job.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samgrayson.me/assets/img/zealots_of_tech/tools.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Chaos of History (part 1)</title><link href="https://samgrayson.me/2016-07-21-chaos-of-history-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Chaos of History (part 1)" /><published>2016-07-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-07-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://samgrayson.me/chaos-of-history-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://samgrayson.me/2016-07-21-chaos-of-history-1/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-man-who-caused-history&quot;&gt;The Man Who Caused History&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of the history of the twentieth century and who is most responsible for
it. You might be thinking of world leaders like Franklin Delano Roosevelt,
Joseph Stalin, or Mao Zedong. Or perhaps you are thinking of those who invented
the technology that changed the world, such as Albert Einstein or Tim
Berners-Lee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I suggest a man you probably haven’t heard of named Gravilo Princip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day started off poorly for Archduke Franz Ferdinand when three security
officials were left behind, by mistake. Then an assassin threw a bomb at his
car! But the bomb bounced off his car and the assassination failed. The
Archduke’s motorcade sped away to protect him from any other assassination
attempts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Ides of March have come, and I am still alive!” – Julius Caesar by
William Shakespeare&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Princip’s realized he lost his chance, so he gave up and went to a
nearby food shop. But when the motorcade started up again, someone
forgot to tell the driver to change the route. When this was realized,
the command was given to reverse, but the transmission was jammed so
the car stopped &lt;em&gt;right in front of an awe-stricken Pincip&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By a ridiculous stroke of misfortune (or luck, depending on your point
of view), between the security officials being left behind, the first
failed assassination attempt, the driver not knowing the route, the
transmission being jammed, Gravilo Princip shot and killed Archduke
Ferdinand&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;princips-butterfly-effect&quot;&gt;Princip’s Butterfly Effect&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might know, this assassination brings up long-standing tensions in
Europe, setting off World War One.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might know, the treaty which ended World War One involved massive war
reparations to be paid by the Germans. The German people came to resent of these
foreign powers spread, making it possible for the Nazis to come to power. Thus
begins World War Two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might know, the victors of World War Two partitioned off Europe, and
while they were doing so, certain tensions among the victors emerged. This led
to the stand off of the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Princip brought about a series of events which caused the Cold War. Or
perhaps the Archduke’s driver should be the one whom we say brought about these
events. Or perhaps the man who owned the food shop that Princip stopped at, for
if he were not there perhaps Princip would gone to a different place that wasn’t
on the motorcade’s route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some would counterargue that the Austro-Hungarian empire was already ripe for
conflict, and if not Princip, then someone else would set it off. But if it was
set off in the middle east as a result of Ottoman aggression (there was unrest
in the region ever since the Young Turk Revolution). Maybe the alignment would
have been different. Russia would not feel compelled to defend the Slavic
peoples, and maybe Russia uses this hypothetical war to seek a warm-water port,
and with the manpower of Russia weighing on the other side of the scale, the
outcome could be drastically different. The specific details of these events can
matter a lot&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;false-assumptions&quot;&gt;False Assumptions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We like to think that systems like human society have some predictable order. We
like to think that this order is affected by world leaders and important
people. We like to think that things happen for compelling reasons. But when a
world war breaks out on account of the chauffeurs wrong turn, I realize that
human society is so vastly complex and intricate that some events are just so
‘out there’ to be foreseen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historical trends and forces are powerful and determine the ‘steady’
events, like the US economy growing a few percentage points per
year. However The most interesting events that really make a change,
like the housing crisis or 9/11, are completely random and unforeseen,
even by scholars. That course of history wasn’t determined by simple
rules ore logical reasons. It’s just Lady Fortuna spinning her wheel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2017-01-09-chaos-of-history-2/&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scientific American: &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/the-curious-wavefunction/gavrilo-princip-conspiracy-theories-and-the-fragility-of-cause-and-effect/&quot;&gt;Gavrilo Princip, conspiracy theories and the fragility of cause and effect&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/chapters/0422-1st-tale.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;Chapter 1&lt;/a&gt; of ‘The Black Swan’ by Nassim Taleb&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Grayson</name></author><category term="history" /><summary type="html">We like to think that systems like human society have some predictable order, when in reality, history is driven by completely unpredictable random events.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://samgrayson.me/assets/img/chaos-of-history-1/Assassination_of_Archduke_Franz_Ferdinand.jpg" /></entry></feed>