<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Interesting Thoughts</title>
    <description>Blog about computers, mathematics, and philosophy. Occasionally, other people find my thoughts on these topics interesting.</description>
    <link>https://samgrayson.me</link>
    <atom:link href="https://samgrayson.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Creative thinking in math class</title>
        <description>
          
          Most students will say math class is stupid and boring. As a math person myself, I have to say: they’re right! Math taught in school is twelve years of Pavlovian training to associate math with arbitrariness and fear. Not only does this rob the student of a potentially enjoyable experience,...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://samgrayson.me/2017-05-20-creative-thinking-in-math-class/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samgrayson.me/2017-05-20-creative-thinking-in-math-class/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Chaos of History (part 2)</title>
        <description>
          
          In a previous post, I talked about how a few random events can greatly change history. In this post, I will describe that idea more mathematically. A Thought Experiment Let’s say I throw a rock straight up into the air and measure how far away it falls 10000 times. I...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>https://samgrayson.me/2017-01-09-chaos-of-history-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samgrayson.me/2017-01-09-chaos-of-history-2/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Zealots of Tech</title>
        <description>
          
          Welcome to the Cult There are few techniques that are globally applicable in software development. But we like to act is if that were not the case. This is most apparent in programming languages. You have headstrong engineers who insist that their programming language is better than yours, with cult-like...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://samgrayson.me/2016-08-12-zealots-of-tech/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samgrayson.me/2016-08-12-zealots-of-tech/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Chaos of History (part 1)</title>
        <description>
          
          The Man Who Caused History Think of the history of the twentieth century and who is most responsible for it. You might be thinking of world leaders like Franklin Delano Roosevelt, Joseph Stalin, or Mao Zedong. Or perhaps you are thinking of those who invented the technology that changed the...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://samgrayson.me/2016-07-21-chaos-of-history-1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samgrayson.me/2016-07-21-chaos-of-history-1/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
