<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"> <channel> <title>Interesting Thoughts</title> <description>Blog about computers, mathematics, and philosophy. Occasionally, other people find my thoughts on these topics interesting.</description> <link>https://samgrayson.me</link> <atom:link href="https://samgrayson.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/> <item> <title>Stop writing shell scripts</title> <description> UNIX shell isn’t a real programming language, so stop using like one! There are occasions one has to use shell due to the structure of UNIX (e.g. the hash-bang, ~/.profile, /etc/init.d/). I won’t indict the REPL because one doesn’t have to maintain what one types in the REPL. As with... </description> <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate> <link>https://samgrayson.me/2021-01-01-shell/</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samgrayson.me/2021-01-01-shell/</guid> </item> <item> <title>The Most Important Constitutional Amendment You've Never Heard Of</title> <description> This amendment lies at the heart of issues on the left and right: granting abortion rights, gay marriage, contraceptive rights, limiting gerrymandering, gun rights, limiting affirmative action, resolving the famous Presidential Election of 2000, and the status of women in the draft. If you care about any of these subjects,... </description> <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate> <link>https://samgrayson.me/2020-12-27-fourteenth/</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samgrayson.me/2020-12-27-fourteenth/</guid> </item> <item> <title>Monads as a Programming Pattern</title> <description> Overview This article is written from a programmer’s perspective, where a monad is a software engineering pattern. Like other patterns, you may have already used it without knowing it was the monad pattern. There is still value in studying such patterns, because then you can use it more fluidly. There... </description> <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate> <link>https://samgrayson.me/2019-08-06-monads-as-a-programming-pattern/</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samgrayson.me/2019-08-06-monads-as-a-programming-pattern/</guid> </item> <item> <title>Creative Thinking in Math Class</title> <description> Most students will say math class is stupid and boring. As a math person myself, I have to say: they’re right! Math taught in school is twelve years of Pavlovian training to associate math with arbitrariness and fear. Not only does this rob the student of a potentially enjoyable experience,... </description> <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate> <link>https://samgrayson.me/2017-05-20-creative-thinking-in-math-class/</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samgrayson.me/2017-05-20-creative-thinking-in-math-class/</guid> </item> <item> <title>The Chaos of History (part 2)</title> <description> In a previous post, I talked about how a few random events can greatly change history. In this post, I will describe that idea more mathematically. A Thought Experiment Let’s say I throw a rock straight up into the air and measure how far away it falls 10000 times. I... </description> <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate> <link>https://samgrayson.me/2017-01-09-chaos-of-history-2/</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samgrayson.me/2017-01-09-chaos-of-history-2/</guid> </item> <item> <title>Zealots of Tech</title> <description> Welcome to the Cult There are few techniques that are globally applicable in software development. But we like to act is if that were not the case. This is most apparent in programming languages. You have headstrong engineers who insist that their programming language is better than yours, with cult-like... </description> <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate> <link>https://samgrayson.me/2016-08-12-zealots-of-tech/</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samgrayson.me/2016-08-12-zealots-of-tech/</guid> </item> <item> <title>The Chaos of History (part 1)</title> <description> One Who Causes History Think of the history of the twentieth century and who is most responsible for it. You might be thinking of world leaders like Franklin Delano Roosevelt, Joseph Stalin, or Mao Zedong. Or perhaps you are thinking of those who invented the technology that changed the world,... </description> <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate> <link>https://samgrayson.me/2016-07-21-chaos-of-history-1/</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">https://samgrayson.me/2016-07-21-chaos-of-history-1/</guid> </item> </channel> </rss>